1. Grubbs - Blood - 1  A 49-year-old man is scheduled for a surgical procedure that will require the long-term use of an anticoagulant after surgery. He is currently being treated for bacterial and protozoal infections with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole and metronidazole. The concurrent use of these medications will require the therapeutic dose of which of the following anticoagulant drugs to be reduced? 
a. aspirin b. desmopressin c. heparin d. streptokinase *e. warfarin  
General Feedback:
	Long-term anticoagulant therapy utilizes warfarin, not heparin, and warfarin is notorious for drug interactions, including the ones listed in the stem. The correct answer is E. Drug interaction enhances warfarins anticoagulant effect. Response A: It is an antiplatelet drug. Response B: It is used to reduce bleeding, not to anticogaulate. Response C: No drug interaction. Response D: This is fibrinolytic drug that would not be useful. 

2. Baumann - Blood - 35  A 73-year-old man is found to have enlarged lymph nodes in his neck and axillae. A biopsy of one of the nodes reveals a follicular center cell lymphoma (low grade). The cells stain intensely by an immunohistochemical technique for bcl-2 protein. What is the molecular pathogenesis of this lymphoma? 
a. adenosine deaminase deficiency b. dysfunction of the retinoic acid receptor c. excessive cell proliferation from cyclin D1 overproduction. d. inability to repair damaged DNA *e. reduced rate of apoptosis  
General Feedback:
	The correct answer is E. Most follicular lymphomas result from t(14;18) which moves the gene for bcl-2 under the influence of an immunoglobulin heavy chain enhancer, causing overexpression of bcl-2, which inhibits apoptosis. Response A: ADA deficiency results in a severe form of congenital immune deficiency. Response B: Dysfunction of a retinoic acid receptor causes acute promyelocytic leukemia. Response C: Overproduction of cyclin D1 results form the t(11;14) characteristic of mantle cell lymphoma. Response D: This is essentially a nonsense answer. 

3. Lockwood - Blood 144  Assuming a normal compensatory physiologic response, which effect is typically seen first in patients with anemia? 
a. decreased reticulocyte count in peripheral blood b. increased erythropoietin release from marrow stem cells c. increased synthesis of hemoglobin F d. shift of oxygen-hemoglobin dissociation curve to left *e. tachycardia  
General Feedback:
	Multiple appropriate compensatory responses to anemia include increased cardiac output, most readily accomplished by tachycardia. Other compensatory responses include: increased reticuloctye count (more young red cells released by marrow), increased erythropoietin release from endothelial cells in peritubular capillaries of the kidney (not marrow stem cells), shift of oxygen-hemoglobin dissociation curve to right (not left). Rate of Hemoglobin F synthesis is not directly affected by anemia. 

4. Martin- 56  Spontaneous rupture of the spleen can be a complication of which of the following diseases? 
*a. infectious mononucleosis b. miliary tuberculosis c. portal thrombosis d. rheumatoid arthritis e. disseminated Histoplasmosis 

5. Lauf - 113 rewrite  A 43-year-old man presents with fatigue, pallor, and icteric sclerae, two weeks after his physician treated a urinary tract infection with a sulfonamide antibiotic. CBC reveals Hgb 9.2 gm/dL(N=14-18 g/dL) with normal WBC and platelet count. This patient's brilliant methyl violet-stained peripheral blood smear shows RBCs containing small violet particles and dots (see photomicograph). These violet dots represent   
a. excess NADP b. lead poisoning *c. precipitates of denatured hemoglobin d. remnants of mitochondria and ribosomes e. residual DNA from RBC nucleus  
General Feedback:
	The patient's male sex, anemia, and evidence of hemolysis following exposure to an oxidant durg (sulfonamide) are suggestive of G6PD deficiency. The photograph shows Heinz bodies with RBC cytoplasm, which are precipitates of denatured hemoglobin that accumulate in patients with G6PD deficiency.