1. Grubbs - Blood - 1  A 49-year-old man is scheduled for a surgical procedure that will require the long-term use of an anticoagulant after surgery. He is currently being treated for bacterial and protozoal infections with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole and metronidazole. The concurrent use of these medications will require the therapeutic dose of which of the following anticoagulant drugs to be reduced? 
a. aspirin b. desmopressin c. heparin d. streptokinase *e. warfarin 
General Feedback:
	Long-term anticoagulant therapy utilizes warfarin, not heparin, and warfarin is notorious for drug interactions, including the ones listed in the stem. The correct answer is E. Drug interaction enhances warfarins anticoagulant effect. Response A: It is an antiplatelet drug. Response B: It is used to reduce bleeding, not to anticogaulate. Response C: No drug interaction. Response D: This is fibrinolytic drug that would not be useful. 

2. Baumann - Blood - 35  A 73-year-old man is found to have enlarged lymph nodes in his neck and axillae. A biopsy of one of the nodes reveals a follicular center cell lymphoma (low grade). The cells stain intensely by an immunohistochemical technique for bcl-2 protein. What is the molecular pathogenesis of this lymphoma? 
a. adenosine deaminase deficiency b. dysfunction of the retinoic acid receptor c. excessive cell proliferation from cyclin D1 overproduction. d. inability to repair damaged DNA *e. reduced rate of apoptosis  
General Feedback:
	The correct answer is E. Most follicular lymphomas result from t(14;18) which moves the gene for bcl-2 under the influence of an immunoglobulin heavy chain enhancer, causing overexpression of bcl-2, which inhibits apoptosis. Response A: ADA deficiency results in a severe form of congenital immune deficiency. Response B: Dysfunction of a retinoic acid receptor causes acute promyelocytic leukemia. Response C: Overproduction of cyclin D1 results form the t(11;14) characteristic of mantle cell lymphoma. Response D: This is essentially a nonsense answer.